我是Animagraffs的作者Jake O'Neal
I'm Jake O'Neal, creator of Animagraffs,
今天向大家介绍机械增压与涡轮增压的工作原理
and this is how superchargers versus turbos work.
机械增压与涡轮增压的基本功能
The basic function of both superchargers and turbos
都是让发动机在燃烧过程中吸入更多空气
is to deliver more air to an engine's internal combustion process.
两者区别如下：
The main distinction between the two is this:
机械增压是由发动机曲轴产生的机械能驱动的
superchargers are mechanically powered,
often by connection to the engine crankshaft,
而涡轮增压是由发动机的废气驱动的
while turbos are powered by engine exhaust gas.
我们来了解下它们各自的原理 先从机械增压说起
Let's look at how each unit works, starting with a supercharger.
视频中所示的机械增压器置于发动机进气歧管上方
The supercharger type shown here sits on top of the air intake manifold.
曲柄输出的能量通过皮带传递给机械增压器的皮带轮上
A serpentine belt transfers crankshaft power to the supercharger pulley.
调整皮带轮的直径与构造
Pulley diameter and construction
就能轻松调整机械增压器的性能参数
is an easily accessible way to quickly alter supercharger performance characteristics.
再通过一套齿轮系统将能量传递给压缩机转子
A gear drive system delivers incoming power to opposing rotors.
外部空气会先流经滤网与进气管
Outside air enters through the air filter and intake pipe.
联锁转子会驱动空气流经机械增压器
Interlocking rotors force air through the supercharger.
联锁转子纵向上的叶片称为凸缘
The long fins or ridges that span the length of the rotor shaft are called "lobes".
空气流出机械增压器时 会通过底部一个形状特别的出口
Air exits the supercharger through a specially shaped discharge port at the bottom of the housing.
以下是机械增压器的几种类型
Here are a few common supercharger types.
鲁式
Roots.
鲁式机械增压器在1900年首次应用在汽车发动机上
The Roots type supercharger saw its first automobile application in 1900.
与其他压缩空气的设计不同 鲁式机械增压最初原型的功能是鼓风机
The term "blower", or "blown engine",
originates from the Roots supercharger's basic function as an air blower,
与其他压缩空气的设计不同 鲁式机械增压最初原型的功能是鼓风机
as opposed to other designs that compress air.
双螺旋式
Twin screw.
双螺旋式机械增压器的特点是具有复杂的转子与设计精巧的凸轮
Twin screw type superchargers feature complex rotors with intricately designed lobes
在空气通过装置时对其进行压缩
that compress air as it moves through the unit.
精密复杂的结构换来的是性能与制造成本的提升
This increased complexity results in better performance but also higher manufacturing cost.
离心式
Centrifugal.
离心式机械增压器和涡轮的设计原理类似
Centrifugal superchargers have much in common with the turbo design concept,
但它仍是由机械能驱动的
though they are still mechanically driven.
该类增压器曲线是指数型的
They produce an exponential power curve,
通常会调教到完全榨干发动机性能的程度
and are often tuned to make full boost at engine redline.
接下来是涡轮增压器的原理
Now let's look at how turbochargers work.
涡轮与发动机排气系统相连
Turbo connects to the engine exhaust system.
涡轮增压装置前排气歧管可能专门为放置涡轮增压器而设计
In turbo setups, the exhaust manifold may be specially designed for turbo placement,
并能处理增加的热量和压力
and to handle increased heat and pressure.
涡轮增压器有两部分组成
The turbo has two separate compartments,
涡轮段
called the turbine section,
和压缩机段
and the compressor section.
废气的热量与压力流经涡轮 驱动其旋转
Exhaust flows to the turbine section as exhaust heat and pressure, drive the turbine or exhaust wheel.
密封的轮轴将废气轮与压缩机轮连接
A sealed shaft connects the exhaust wheel to the compressor wheel.
外部空气流经滤网和进气管后 被压缩机轮吸入
The compressor wheel pulls air in through the air filter and intake pipe.
压缩机内特殊形状的叶片使空气进入一段缩窄的腔室 实现压缩
It's specially shaped fins force air through an increasingly smaller chamber, building compression.
进气与压缩的过程中 空气温度会升高
Air gets hot during intake and compression,
所以多数涡轮增压器会在涡轮与发动机之间配置中冷器
so most turbo setups have an intercooler between the turbo and engine intake,
让空气冷却到合适的温度
to get air back down to ambient temperatures.
低温的空气密度更大
Cooler air has greater density,
实现让发动机吸入更多空气的目标
serving the goal of forcing more air into the engine.
中冷器原理和散热器类似
The intercooler works something like a radiator.
热空气流过内部管道 而外面的空气急速流过冷排 实现冷却
Hot air passes through internal tubes as outside air rushes by for cooling.
以下是一些常见的涡轮设计
Here are some common turbo designs
单涡轮式 所有废气都流经这一个涡轮增压器
The single turbo shown here where all exhaust flows through a single turbocharger.
双涡轮式
Twin turbo.
每套装置有两组涡轮增压器
A setup with two turbochargers,
比如V6发动机 每侧各一个涡轮
for example on a six-cylinder Engine with one turbo for each cylinder bank.
双涡流式涡轮增压
Twin-scroll turbo.
废气是以一次次高压脉冲的形式从气缸中排出的
Exhaust exits the cylinder in a pulse with a high pressure section followed by low pressure.
双涡流式涡轮增压器可以把气缸分组
Twin scroll turbos separate cylinders into pairs,
让一波波废气之间不会互相干涉
so that exhaust pulse waves do not interfere with each other.
让到达涡轮的废气流压力更高 更连续
And a continuous stream of maximum pressure exhaust reaches the turbine.
接下来我们大致对比一下两种增压器
Now let's compare superchargers and turbos in very general terms.
机械增压是由发动机的机械能驱动的
Again superchargers are powered by mechanical energy,
比如与发动机曲柄相连
for example by connection to an engine's crankshaft,
而涡轮增压则是用发动机原本浪费的热量驱动的
while turbos are powered by otherwise wasted heat energy from engine exhaust.
增压特性
Boost characteristics.
鲁式和双螺旋式机械增压都使用容积式压缩机
Roots and twin screw superchargers have positive-displacement,
发动机每转一周 它都会挤压相同体积的空气 与转速无关
meaning that they move the same amount of air for each engine revolution, regardless of RPM.
同时 它们在低转速下仍能立即获得增压效果
This also means that they can make boost immediately, even at very low RPMs,
并有一个相当线性的功率曲线
and have a fairly linear power curve.
涡轮增压的功率曲线是指数型的
Turbo setups produce an exponential power curve,
因其是由废气驱动的
since they are powered by exhaust,
所以涡轮在实现可用增压之前需要时间起转达速 达到压力
turbos take time to build turbine speed and pressure before producing usable boost.
该现象称为涡轮迟滞
This delay is called turbo lag.
效率
Efficiency.
机械增压需要动力来创造动力
Superchargers take power to make power,
平均下来 需要40-60马力的功率才能运行
and an average setup can require 40 to 60 horsepower to function.
但并不能说这样会牺牲发动机的整体效率
This doesn't mean that overall engine efficiency is always sacrificed,
因为调教好了 正常开的话是提升燃油效率的
as some setups can increase fuel economy when not driven aggressively.
虽然涡轮增压会增加发动机的背压
Though turbos do increase back pressure on the engine,
但驱动它们的主要是废气的热量 而不是废气气流的压力
they derive power primarily from otherwise wasted exhaust heat as opposed to exhaust flow pressure.
因此 它们可以非常高效
As such they can be very efficient.
结论上看 机械增压是一种相对简单、廉价的提高发动机性能的方法
In conclusion, superchargers can be a less complex less expensive way to increase engine performance,
易于调教与维护
they're usually easier to tune and maintain.
如果需要在所有转速下都能增压 那么机械增压是理想的选择
They can be ideal in applications that require predictable boost at all RPMs.
涡轮增压需要更多的改装组件
Turbos might require more peripheral parts,
比如油路与真空管线 中冷器 定制排气歧管 排气管等等
like oil and vacuum lines, an intercooler, custom exhaust manifolds and exhaust piping and so on.
还需要更高的技术进行调教
Turbos can require more skill to properly configure.
而精心调校过的涡轮增压系统可以比机械增压效率更高 增压量更大
However, a well-tuned turbo system may be able to produce boost more efficiently,
and in greater quantity than a supercharger.